Guide to the Lincoln Collection Sheet Music 1836-1878
University of Chicago Library
- Series IV: Civil War Song Sheets
  - THE BATTLE OF THE WILDERNESS, "Now boys just listen while I sing to you a song" sirs, (10 vs. and chor.) Wolf #106 variant a -- Composed, published and sung by James D. Gay; cop: 1864 James D. Gay, EDPa., A-J border. 23.2 x 14.7 cm. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - BOSTON TEA-PARTY, "Once on a time, old Johnny Bull got in a raging fury" (4vs. and chor.) Wolf #182 variant a -- Publ. De Marsan De Marsan horned imp border. 24.6 x 16.0 cm. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - THE CAPTURE OF JEFF. DAVIS, "Haste. haste, and eat your breakfast, boys" (7 vs.) Vs. headed "Say, Does He Fancy He Does See That ‘Horrible Hour Apple Tree’?" [signed] DE WOLFE Wolf #247 variant unlisted -- Published and sold Wholesale by Horace Partridge, Boston. Adv. Fancy goods, Toys, Watches, etc., T.o. border. 18.0 x 11.7 cm. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - THE CONSTITUTION!, "Oh, God, preserve the Union" (3 vs. and chor.) National anthem, written, composed and respectfully dedicated to the President and People of the United States, by F. Widdows; sung by James Dunn Esq; Music Published by Firth, Pond & Co. (Publ.) De Marsan. Wolf #380 De Marsan ship border. col. 25.8 x 17.0 cm. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - DEATH OF PRESIDENT LINCOLN!, "’Twas on that sad and mournful night" (4vs.) Air -- Sword of Bunker Hill. Cop: 1865, James D. Gay, EDPa. Wolf #463 variant a -- Following title: Born February 12, 1809: -- Died April 15th, 1865.; composed April 23rd, 1865, by James D. Gay, Mourning border bust of Lincoln within flagged wreath with mourning soldier and woman at sides. 26.7 x 19.8 cm. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - DEDICATED TO THE MEMORY OF ABRAHAM LINCOLN., "America's noblest sons are weeping." (8 lines) Cop. 1865. James Logan. EDPa. Wolf #468 Mourning border. 24.4 x 20 cm. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - DON'T BE CHOKED OFF, "Now, kind folks, give attention (4 vs.) Air: Young Gal from New-Jersey. By John C. Cross Wolf #507 variant a -- [Publ.] De Marsan De Marsan military cupid border. 24.5 x 16.2 cm. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - THE DYING PATRIOT, "Native land! oh! dear sweet home" (3 vs.) Air: The Last Rose of Summer Wolf #544 variant unlisted -- publ. De Marsan Wrigley kissing cupid border. 25.5 x 15.5 cm. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - THE GALLANT SOLDIER, "When war-drums beat and cannons rattle, sage and sire stories tell" (7 vs. Air: The Storm Wolf 3709 variant a -- Publ. De Marsan De Marsan comic heads border. 25.4 x 16.9 cm. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - GAY AND HAPPY, "I'm the girl that's gay and happy (8 vs. and chor) composed and sung by Miss Annie Rush, the Philadelphia Vocalist. Wolf #717 variant c -- (without "The Philadelphia Vocalist") publ. De Marsan De Marsan Clown Border. 25.5 x 16.5 cm. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - GENERAL GRANT'S BOYS, "Ye copperheads and traitors, to you these lines we write" (4 vs. and chor.) Cop: 1864, James D. Gay, EDPa. Wolf #724 variant a -- with "Gen." in title; by James D. Gay, the celebrated Army Song Publisher and Vocalist T.o border, battle scene with line of charging soldiers within ornamental frame. 23.7 x 14.9 cm. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - THE GLORIOUS STRIPES & STARS, "Come all, you loyal Patriots, many may there be" (8 vs.) Air: George Reilly. Wolf #758 variant a -- Publ. De Marsan De Marsan eagle border, col. 25.4 x 16.5 cm. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - GOOD MORNING, MASTER LINCOLN!, "Good morning, Master Lincoln" (8 vs. and chor.) (Melody -- "Wait for the Waton," etc.) by Max Langenschwarz; cop.; 1864, Max Langenschwarz. SDN. Y. Wolf #783 Letter paper; blue ink; hdpc. Magnus 68 (see Wolf's numbers), col. publ. Magnus. 20.3 x 12.7 cm. (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - GOOD-BYE, ALLIE DEAR!, "It's when I'm far away from home (4 vs. and chor.) 2nd song: "One Kindly Word Before We Part" Wolf #700 variant a -- As sung by R. Simpson: publ. De Marsan De Marsan fountain border. 25.4 x 16.4 cm. (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - HOIST UP THE FLAG, "Away down in Dixie, the war first begun" (7 vs. and chor.) Wolf #833 variant h -- Without period at end of title with "New" before title: Words and melody by Billy Holmes; music arranged by Sep. Winner; adv.: Prof. Brooks' Ball Room Monitor; publ. Johnson, A-J border. 24.4 x 14.7 cm. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - HOW ARE YOU, GREEN BACKS?, "We're coming, Father Abram, one hundred thousand more" (7 vs.) Music ad of Wm. A. Pond & Co. Wolf #912 variant c -- With hyphen in title; "One" in first line; last 2 lines of each vs. marked as chorus; varying: "Music obtained at Wm. A. Pond & Co.; Publ. De Marsan. variant g -- With hyphen in title; "One" in first line. Letter paper; blue ink. hdpc. Magnus 216. col; publ. Magnus. 20.0 x 12.5 cm. (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - A HUNDRED YEARS HENCE, "We meet through this world with men of all kinds" (8 vs.) written and sung by Tony Pastor. Wolf #929 variant e -- Varying: "Written and sung by Tony Paster, with great applause at the American Theatre, 444 Broadway, N.Y.; adv: 500 Illustrated Ballads. publ. Magnus, Letter paper; blue ink; hdpc. Magnus 35, col; publ. Magnus. 20.5 x 13.0 cm. (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - THE IRISH WIDE AWAKE., "As I walked out one evening" (4 vs. and chor.) Air: Billy O'Rourke. by Harry M. Palmer; publ. De Marsan Wolf #1067 De Marsan trapper border, col.; cop:1860, H. De Marsan SDN.Y. 25.3 x 16.2 cm. (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - JEFFIE D. OR, THE PETTICOATED PRESIDENT, "With Bowie-knife, in guise of wife" (8 vs. and chor.) Tune: "Yankee Doodle" Wolf #1102 T.o. border; 18.3 x 11.2 cm. (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - JOHNNY, FILL UP THE BOWL!, "Abram Lincoln, what yer 'bout" (4 vs.) Wolf #1139 variant c -- Composed by Saul Sertrew; Free-and-Easy Song; publ. De Marsan De Marsan clown border. 26.0 x 16.4 cm. (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - KEYSTONE BRIGADE, "Hurray for our brave Pennsylvanians" (7 vs.) Air: -- Columbia, the Gem of the Ocean. Wolf #1182 variant c -- without comma after "Columbia" in air; Composed by Lieut. James D. Gay of Philadelphia; formerly a member of the Ringgold Artillery.. .; copyright secured. adv.: Sold Wholesale at 300 North 20th St. A-J border; seal of Pennsylvania, 23.5 x 15.5 cm. (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - KINGDOM COMING, "Say, darkeys, hab you seen de Massa" (4 vs. and chor.) by Henry C. Work Wolf #1188 variant e -- With the first line reading: "Sa Darkies! did you see ole massa"; As Originally Sung by Mrs. C. Henri, Arch Street Theatre; with advs: Cards, Bill Heads, Circulars, etc. and Ball Room Monitor; publ. Johnson. seated man waving top hat, 23.9 x 14.8 cm. variant f -- As above without advs.; publ. Johnson; 2nd Song, "THAT'S WHAT'S THE MATTER," 24.4 x 15.2 cm (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - MEMORIES OF THE PAST., "O, Memories of the past! ye come" (2 vs) Wolf #1417 variant a -- Publ. De Marsan De Marsan eagle border. col. 24.7 x 16.7 cm. (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - MY LOVE IS A ZOU-ZU., "My love is a Zou-zu, so gallant and bold" (4 vs. and chor.) Wolf #1515 variant c -- Title: "My Love He Is A Zou-Zu. Only 19 Years Old"; only one chor.; without comma in the first line; publ. de Marsan De Marson border with eagle, drapery with stars and stripes. col. 24.0 x 14.8 cm. (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - THE NATION IS WEEPING, "Lincoln has fallen! the good and great!" (4 vs. and chor.) Air:- Under the willow she's sleeping. by Louise S. Upham Wolf #1543 variant unlisted -- With "Willow" in Air; publ. Magnus. black border. hdpc. Magnus 9. 20.3 x 12.6 cm. (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - THE NATION MOURNS., "From all churches" (5 vs.) Wolf #1544 variant b -- Publ. Magnus Letter paper; hdpc. Magnus 7. 20.4 x 12.5 cm. (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - THE NORTHMEN ARE COMING!, "The Northmen are coming, Oho! Oho!" (5 vs.) Air: The Campbells are coming. by George Perry Wolf #1624 variant a -- Publ. De Marsan De Marsan eagle border. col. 25.8 x 16.2 cm. (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - THE OLD UNION WAGON., "The eagle of Columbia, in majesty and pride" (5 vs. and chor.) Wolf #1736 variant b -- Without "The" in title and without period at end; but with Air:- Wait for the Wagon; with 4th vs. beginning: "Old Abe is in the wagon, and McClellan by his side.. ."; publ. Auner, A-J border. 23.4 x 14.5 cm. (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - THE OLD UNION WAGON, variant d -- Air as above with 7 vs. and chor. variant in wording of vs.; by James D. Gay, the celebrated Army Song Publisher and Vocalist; cop: 1864, James D. Gay, EDPa t.o. border; eagle and shield with motto: "E Pluribus Unum." 24.0 x 15.0 cm. variant f -- Title: "Abe Lincoln's Union Wagon"; with 7 vs. and chor.; variant in wording of vs.; Air "Wait for the Wagon," or "Old Virginia low lands"; by James D. Gay Army Songer Dealer and Publisher; adv.: All of Gay's Army Songs; cop: 1864, James D. Gay, EDPa. Letter paper; blue ink; hdpc. Magnus 8. col. Publ. Magnus. 20.4 x 12.5 cm. (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - ON! ON! ON! A SEQUEL TO TRAMP, TRAMP, TRAMP!, "Oh the day it came, at last" (3 vs. and chor.) Music published by Root & Cady. Wolf #1745 variant d -- Title: "On! On! On! the Boys Came Marching"; Air - "Prisoner's Hope." music publ. by Root and Co. A-J border. 20.4 x 12.5 cm (trimmed) (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - OUR COUNTRY., "Our Country! ‘Tis of thee we sing" (7 vs.) Air: Old Hundred. Wolf #1772 variant a -- Publ. De Marsan De Marsan lyre border. 25.2 x 17.0 cm. (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - OUR GERMAN VOLUNTEERS., "There is a General in the West Whose deeds have come to fame" (5 vs.) Air:- New-York Volunteer. Wolf #1787 variant a -- publ. De Marsan De Marsan eagle border, col. 24.9 x 17.0 cm. (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - OUR GLORIOUS FLAG RED WHITE AND BLUE., "Come to the field of fame, boys, come" (6 vs.) Air:- The Rich Girl Wolf #1788 variant a -- Publ. De Marsan De Marsan eagle border, col. 24.5 x 17.3 cm. (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - THE SOLDIER'S DEATHBED., "Like thee to die, thou sun! -- My boyhood's dream" (40 lines) by Mrs. Felicia Hemans; Sept. 1863; print. Johnson; (with letter calling for votes from National Union Executive Committee of the Ward on verso) Wolf #2144 double line border. 20.4 x 13.0 cm. (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - SONG ON THE DEATH OF PRESIDENT ABRAHAM LINCOLN., "Halls and homes in black are shrouded" (5 vs.) Tune:-Annie Laurie. by Silas S. Steele. Wolf #2205 variant a -- Cop: 1865, J. Magee. Letter paper; mourning border, 20.3 x 13.0 cm. (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - STRIKING ILE., "The world it revolves on its own axle-tree" (7 vs. and chor.) Words by Dan D. Emmett; music obtained of Wm. A. Pond & Co. Wolf #2257 variant a -- Publ. De Marsan De Marsan Etheopian border. 24.7 x 16.3 cm. (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - UNCLE SAM'S FENCE., "Of all the mighty Nations, in the East or in the West" (5 vs. and chor.) Tune. Walk in de Parlor and hear de Banjo Play. Wolf #2394 variant g -- Title: "Uncle Sam's Fence" with 10 vs. and chor. slightly varying; "Tune – ‘Uncle Sam's Farm'" print. Johnson. 23.8 x 14.3 cm. (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - THE UNION FOR EVER FOR ME!, "American! Gem of this wide, wide world (3 vs. and chor.) Publ. De Marsan Wolf #2422 De Marsan Ship border, with war scenes in lower corners. 25.6 x 16.4 cm. (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - THE UNION MUST AND SHALL BE PRESERVED, "O say, can a thought so vile and base come." (4 vs.) Air: Star-Spangled Banner. Wolf #2427 variant a -- Publ. De Marsan De Marsan eagle border, col. 25.2 x 16.5 cm. (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - VENGEONS LA PATRIE., "Debout, Fils de l'Union" (3 vs. and chor.) Air: Gloire aux martyrs victorieux! Hymn patriotique par Gustave Dime, ourier-estampeur; publ. De Marsan Wolf #2450 De Marsan eagle border, col. 25.5 x 16.3 cm. (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - WAR SONG OF THE NEW-YORK 69th REGIMENT., "The country calls thee, Sixty-ninth" (5 vs. and chor.) Publ. De Marsan Wolf #2492 De Marsan eagle border, col. 26.0 x 16.8 cm. (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - WAR-SONG OF THE UNION, "To arms, Ye Brave! obey your Country's call" (4 vs. and chor.) Air: The Standard Bearer Wolf #2494 variant a -- Publ. De Marsan De Marsan eagle border, col. 26.0 x 17.0 cm. (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - WE ARE COMING, FATHER ABRAHAM, 600,000 MORE., "We are coming father Abraham, six hundred thousand more" (4 vs.) by James Sloan Gibbons Wolf #2500 variant f -- Without comma after "Coming" in title; with last part of verses indented as chor.; words by J. Cullen Bryant; music by D. A. Warden; song with Piano accompaniment had at Johnson's; publ. Johnson. 24.0 x 15.0 cm. (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - WE ARE FOR THE UNION., "Our Flag and the Union! in the North is the cry" (4 vs. and chor.) Air:-Gay and Happy Wolf #2513 variant b -- Title: "Our Country's Flag; with quotation marks enclosing, "Our Flag and the "Union" in first line; publ. De Marsan. De Marsan eagle border, col. 24.5 x 16.3 cm. (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - WHERE LIBERTY DWELLS, THERE IS MY COUNTRY, "Where Liberty dwells is my country." (5 vs. and chor.) Wolf #2595 variant b -- Music had a Horace Waters. Publ. De Marsan De Marsan ship border. (no war scenes) 25.5 x 16.0 cm. (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - THE WIDE-AWAKES., "O, what is all this noise about" (6 vs. and chor.) Wolf #2631 variant a -- by O.P.Q.; Air:-Washing Day; publ. De Marsan. De Marsan clown border, col.; cop:1860, H. De Marsan, SDN.Y. 25.7 x 16.7 cm. (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - THE YANKEE BOY., "A Yankee Boy is trim and tall" (5 vs. and chor.) Air:- Yankee Doodle by Isadore Leopold; publ. De Marsan Wolf #2681 De Marsan flag border with center star. col. 24.8 x 16.0 cm. (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - YANKEE BOYS, SO HANDY, O!, "It always has been told" (5 vs.) Wolf #2682 variant e -- Without comma after "Boys"; Tune. -- Yankee Doodle Dandy; adv. Cards, Circulars, Bill-Heads, etc.; publ. Johnson. A-J border, 24.8 x 15.3 cm. (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - DAILY SONG OF THE HUNDRED DAY SOLDIER., "I want to go home, I want to go home" (14 vs.) written for the Cincinnati Times. J.A.R., Co. G, 139th Ohio National Guards. Not in Wolf. with REPLY OF THE ILLINOIS HUNDRED DAY SOLDIERS... on recto. 35.0 x 10.0 cm. (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - REPLY OF THE ILLINOIS HUNDRED DAY SOLDIERS TO THE DAILY SONG OF THE OHIO HUNDRED DAY SOLDIERS, PUBLISHED IN THE CINCINNATO WEEKLY TIMES, JULY 28, 1864., "We have seen the report you have made of the boys:" (12 vs.) by Lafayette Sweet. 2nd Sarg't Co. II., 143d Illinois Vol. Not in Wolf. with DAILY SONG OF THE HUNDRED DAY SOLDIER. on verso. 35.0 x 10.0 cm. (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - DIRGE, "Unveil thy bosom, faithful tomb"... as sung at the Funeral Ceremonies of the President Abraham Lincoln, at Springfield, Ills. Thursday, May 4, 1865. "Unveil thy bosom, faithful tomb:" (4 vs.) F. Kluender, Printer. St. Louis, Mo. Not in Wolf. Black mourning border. 26.9 x 13.9 cm. (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - FUNERAL HYMN., "Rest, noble Martyr! rest in peace:" (5 vs. plus Doxology) by the Rev. P. D. Gurley, D.D. Not in Wolf. Mourning border. 12.5 x 8.2 trimmed. (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - THE PRESIDENTS' (sic) ASSASSINATION., "Will you listen, brother Henry, to the tolling of the bell?" (7 vs.) by DeWolfe, W. P. of H. N. Not in Wolf. Mourning border. head of Lincoln with four lines of verse written vertically. 20.1 x 12.0 cm. (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - GRANT CAMPAIGN SONG., "We are Coming Brave Ulysses". -- "We are coming Gen'ral Grant, with one hundred thousand more." (4 vs. and chor.) paraphrased by R. Allen Jr. music by J. Lloyd, Jr. Not in Wolf. 6 staves of music. 26.0 x 17.0 handwritten description on recto. (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - LONG LIVE THE UNION!, A Hymn for the Nation on the Return of Peace. Addressed to the Union Associations, Loyal Leagues, and Loyal People of the United States. -- "Upheld and guarded by the "Almighty Power," (8 vs. and chor.) by C. J. Warren. Harmonized by H. G. Abbey Music, an old National Air. Not in Wolf. 3 staves of music included. adv. at bottom. Peace Restored, Rebellion Subdued, etc.... 23.0 x 20.0 cm. (Box 4, Folder 34)